draw the circle of radius 1 at the
origin rotate an angle Theta the point
on the unit circle for Theta has an x
coordinate of cosine Theta and a
y-coordinate of sin Theta if we draw the
tangent line to the circle at the point
and connect to the x-axis by triangle
similarity the distance labeled D here
satisfies d/ 1 is equal to sin thet over
cosine thet which is the tangent of thet
also by triangle similarity the
hypotenuse of the picture triangle is 1
over the cosine of theta so it's the
secant of theta if we extend the tangent
line to the Y AIS like this then the two
picture triangles are similar so that
the labeled distance D satisfies D 1al
cosine Theta over sin Theta which is the
cent of theta and the hypotenuse of the
green triangle is 1/ sin Theta which is
cosecant Theta these definitions of the
six standard trig functions can be
extended to the other quadrants as well
and this animation demonstrates their
range restrictions the prefix Co stands
for complimentary because the two
picture triangles have complimentary
angles Theta and pi/ 2 minus Theta so
the cosine is the sign of the
complimentary angle